[
    {
        "category": "Myth",
        "question": "What son of Aethlius and Calyce, known as the 'sleeping beauty' of Greek mythology, was prominently featured on Roman sarcophagi?",
        "answer": "Endymion"
    },
    {
        "category": "Myth", 
        "question": "What goddess fell in love with Endymion and bore him fifty sons?",
        "answer": "Selene"
    },
    {
        "category": "Myth",
        "question": "Which off-limits goddess did Endymion seduce, leading to trouble in Olympus?",
        "answer": "Hera"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "What Latin author satirized city life and scandalous activities while romanticizing his provincial upbringing in his *Epigrams*?",
        "answer": "Martial"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Of what Roman province was Martial a native?",
        "answer": "Hispania/Spain"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Translate Martial's lines: 'Non amo te, Sabidi, nec possum dicere quare; Hoc tantum possum dicere, non amo te.'",
        "answer": "'I do not love you, Sabidius; I cannot say why. I am only able to say this: I do not love you.'"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What was unique about the way an *Essedarius* gladiator fought?",
        "answer": "He fought from a chariot."
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What type of gladiator faced the disadvantage of being blindfolded?",
        "answer": "Andabata"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Through which gateway would an unlucky Andabata exit the arena?",
        "answer": "The Porta Libitinensis"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Who founded a new city on the site of Byzantium in 324 AD?",
        "answer": "Constantine"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What city did Constantine found?",
        "answer": "Constantinople"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What famous victory by Constantine over Maxentius in 312 AD did the city commemorate?",
        "answer": "The Battle of the Milvian Bridge"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What is the Latin phrase for 'there is no accounting for taste'?",
        "answer": "De gustibus non est disputandum."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What is the Latin phrase for 'without end'?",
        "answer": "Ad infinitum"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What is the Latin phrase for 'at first sight'?",
        "answer": "Prima facie"
    },
    {
        "category": "Myth",
        "question": "What king pursued Britomartis for nine months until she jumped into the sea to escape?",
        "answer": "Minos"
    },
    {
        "category": "Myth",
        "question": "What was Britomartis' deified name?",
        "answer": "Dictynna"
    },
    {
        "category": "Myth",
        "question": "Which daughter of Minos bore children by Apollo and was banished to Libya?",
        "answer": "Acacallis"
    }, 
     {
        "category": "Philosophy",
        "question": "What philosophical work of Cicero was preserved in part by a commentary of Macrobius and partly only on palimpsests?",
        "answer": "De Re Publica"
    },
    {
        "category": "Philosophy",
        "question": "What special name is given to the sixth book of De Re Publica?",
        "answer": "Somnium Scipionis"
    },
    {
        "category": "Philosophy",
        "question": "Who is the Scipio that Cicero refers to?",
        "answer": "Scipio Aemilianus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate the sentence 'Servi coxerunt cenam ne magister illos verberaret.' into English.",
        "answer": "The slaves cooked dinner so that their master would not beat them."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate the sentence 'Timeo ne mei servi me occidere temptent.' into English.",
        "answer": "I fear that my slaves may try to kill me."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate the sentence 'Magister cucurrit quo celerius servos evitaret.' into English.",
        "answer": "The master fled to more quickly avoid the slaves."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What Latin phrase can be used to mean 'there is no accounting for taste?'",
        "answer": "De gustibus non est disputandum."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What Latin phrase can be used to mean 'without end?'",
        "answer": "Ad infinitum"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What Latin phrase can be used to mean 'at first sight?'",
        "answer": "Prima facie"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "During his military career, Caesar suffered two defeats of note. Who was the Gallic commander in the first defeat during the Gallic wars in 52 B.C.?",
        "answer": "Vercingetorix"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Where did this battle take place?",
        "answer": "Gergovia"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Caesar's other defeat came at the hands of his chief rival, Pompey Magnus. Where and when did this battle occur?",
        "answer": "Dyrrhachium, 48 B.C."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Give an antonym of 'turpis.'",
        "answer": "Pulcher/Formosus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Give a synonym of 'intentus.'",
        "answer": "Studiosus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Give an antonym of 'mane.'",
        "answer": "Noctu/Sero"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Identify the speaker of the following lines from the Aeneid: 'O terque quaterque beati, quis ante ora partum Troiae sub moenibus altis contigit oppetere!'",
        "answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Who does Aeneas believe are 'terque quaterque beati'?",
        "answer": "Those who died defending Troy"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "For the verb rideo, give the first person plural perfect active subjunctive.",
        "answer": "Riserimus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Give the masculine plural dative perfect participle of 'cado, cadere.'",
        "answer": "Casis"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate into Latin: 'We would have laughed, if the teacher was not standing nearby.'",
        "answer": "Riserimus, si magister non prope steterit."
    },
     {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What were Ennius' three hearts?",
        "answer": "Oscan, Greek, Latin (He could speak those three languages)."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "In the introduction of what work does Ennius make the claim mentioned in the toss-up?",
        "answer": "Annales/Annals"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What Greek god had the epithet Loxias?",
        "answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What Greek god had the epithet Bromios?",
        "answer": "Dionysus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What Greek god had the epithet Enyalius?",
        "answer": "Ares"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What hero, born Alcides, was renamed in an attempt to appease his stepmother's wrath?",
        "answer": "Heracles"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What hero was born with the name Ligyron?",
        "answer": "Achilles"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What hero was deified with the name Indiges?",
        "answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the nouns Bos and Mos.",
        "answer": "Bos - Cow, Mos - Custom/Habit"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Differentiate between the nouns Frons and Fons.",
        "answer": "Frons - Forehead or Leaf, Fons - Fountain, Spring"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Differentiate between the nouns Pontus and Pondus.",
        "answer": "Pontus - Sea, Pondus - Burden/Weight"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What two groups of brothers fought to determine the outcome of the war between Rome and Alba Longa?",
        "answer": "Horatii and Curiatii"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Who was the king of Alba Longa at the time?",
        "answer": "Mettius Fufetius"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "Who was the king of Rome who would later destroy Alba Longa?",
        "answer": "Tullus Hostilius"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate into English: 'Si vicisset, laeta fuisset.'",
        "answer": "If she had won, she would have been happy."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What type of condition is illustrated in 'Si vicisset, laeta fuisset'?",
        "answer": "Past contrary to fact"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Translate this sentence into English: 'Si fias optimus lusor certaminis, omnes te ament.'",
        "answer": "If you should become the best Certamen player, everyone would love you."
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What tribe's capital city was Themiscyra?",
        "answer": "The Amazons"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What tribe was ruled by the boxing king Amycus?",
        "answer": "The Bebryces"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What tribe clashed their spears and swords against their shields to hide the infant Zeus' existence?",
        "answer": "The Curetes or Corybantes"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "What Augustan age prolific author was banished to Tomi for 'Carmen et Error'?",
        "answer": "Ovid"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "What book of sad lamentations did Ovid write during his exile?",
        "answer": "Tristia"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What war began with the Roman people's vote to send an army overseas for the first time in 264 BC?",
        "answer": "First Punic War"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "What group, which had captured Messana, invited the Romans to interfere in Sicily?",
        "answer": "Mamertines"
    },
    {
        "category": "History",
        "question": "In what year had the Mamertines seized Messana?",
        "answer": "288 BC"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Give the accusative plural of the phrase 'the same two farmers'.",
        "answer": "Eosdem duos agricolas"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Make 'eosdem duos agricolas' genitive.",
        "answer": "Eorundem duorum agricolarum"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Make 'eorundem duorum agricolarum' dative.",
        "answer": "Eisdem duobus agricolis"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Identify the figure of speech in the following Latin quotation from Catullus: 'Odi et amo. Quare id faciam, fortasse requiris. Nescio, sed fieri sentio et excrucior.'",
        "answer": "Chiasmus or Antithesis"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Identify the figure of speech excluding alliteration in the following Latin quotation from Ennius: 'At tuba terribili sonitu taratantara dixit.'",
        "answer": "Onomatopoeia"
    },
    {
        "category": "Literature",
        "question": "Identify the figure of speech in the following Latin quotation from Ennius: 'Saxo cere comminuit brum.'",
        "answer": "Tmesis"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "Name any six of the Seven Against Thebes according to the traditional account of Aeschylus.",
        "answer": "Adrastus, Amphiaraus, Capaneus, Hippomedon, Parthenopaeus, Polyneices, Tydeus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "Name the two allies of the Seven who also perished in the battle.",
        "answer": "Eteoclus (not Eteocles) and Mecisteus"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "Why did the first brother want the most powerful wand?",
        "answer": "To kill his enemy"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What killed the second brother?",
        "answer": "Grief (of his dead girlfriend)"
    },
    {
        "category": "Mythology",
        "question": "What was unusual about the third brother's cloak?",
        "answer": "He could not be seen under it"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "What is this man saying: 'Potesne me docere quomodo dugias?' Assuming the verb 'dugio, dugere' means 'to dougie.'",
        "answer": "Can you teach me how to dougie?"
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Upon teaching this man your sweet 'dougie-ing' skills a woman comments: 'Habes motūs tamquam es Iagger.' What is this woman saying?",
        "answer": "You have moves like Jagger."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Perform the following command: 'Nunc demonstrate, vos omnes, spectatoribus tuos dulces motus (long u) saltando.'",
        "answer": "All the players should show the spectators their sweet dance moves by dancing."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Perform the following command: 'Sta, age ad sinistrum, age retro, deinde sali semel.'",
        "answer": "The student should get up, go to the left, go backwards, and jump once."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Perform the following command: 'Nunc omnes ostendete dextros, deinde illos retrahite, deinde ostendete pedes sinistros, deinde illos retrahite.'",
        "answer": "The team should extend their right hands, retract their right hands, extend their left feet, then retract their left feet."
    },
    {
        "category": "Language",
        "question": "Perform the following command: 'Agite tamquam togae tuae ardeant!'",
        "answer": "The team should act as though their togas were on fire."
    },
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Stoic satirist claimed that his muse was his stomach or belly?",
    "answer": "Persius"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was Persius' teacher and cherished friend, eulogized in the fifth satire?",
    "answer": "Cornutus"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says that his own works are trivial when compared to those of Persius?",
    "answer": "Lucan"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: 'Certamen is wonderful to play.'",
    "answer": "Certamen est mirabile lusu"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: 'It is hard to win.'",
    "answer": "Vincere est difficile"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin using a subjunctive in the singular: 'Don't think too hard.'",
    "answer": "Cave putes durius / Ne putaveris durius"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was the son of the goddess of love and the Argonaut Butes?",
    "answer": "Eryx"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who killed Eryx in a wrestling match?",
    "answer": "Heracles"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What later hero worshipped Eryx as his ancestor?",
    "answer": "Aeneas"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman ruler willingly resigned power after three years in power?",
    "answer": "Sulla"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who did Sulla deny a triumph in 80 B.C.?",
    "answer": "Pompey"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who violated Sulla's law by daring to stand for the consulship against him?",
    "answer": "Quintus Lucretius Ofella"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who, the eldest son of Heracles and Deineira, married his father's concubine Iole and took revenge against Eurystheus by capturing and/or killing him?",
    "answer": "Hyllus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who killed Hyllus in single combat during the expedition of the Heraclids?",
    "answer": "Echemus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was the son of Hyllus by Iole?",
    "answer": "Cleodaeus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb 'scio' means pleasing, agreeable, or delightful?",
    "answer": "Nice"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb 'nascor' means showing a lack of experience, wisdom, or judgment?",
    "answer": "Naïve"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb 'vinco' means to reveal the presence of?",
    "answer": "Evince"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which, if any, of these provinces was not fully conquered during the reign of Claudius? Thrace, Noricum, Pamphylia, Lycia, Judaea, Britain.",
    "answer": "Britain"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What relation, besides adopted son, did Claudius have with his successor Nero?",
    "answer": "Claudius was Nero's great uncle"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What ancestor of Nero had been a staunch enemy of Caesar, served as consul in 54 B.C., and fought against Caesar at the Battle of Pharsalus?",
    "answer": "L. Domitius Ahenobarbus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The motto of the University of Chicago is Crescat scientia; vita excolatur. What is this motto translated into English?",
    "answer": "Let knowledge grow; (and so) life be improved"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What type of subjunctive is found in the phrase Crescat scientia?",
    "answer": "Jussive subjunctive"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The motto of Miami University is Prodesse quam conspici. What is this phrase in English?",
    "answer": "To achieve (be beneficial, etc.) rather than to be seen"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What Titaness married Hyperion and gave birth to Helius, Eos, and Selene?",
    "answer": "Theia / Euryphaessa"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Give an alternate name for this Titaness.",
    "answer": "Theia / Euryphaessa"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Other than wife, what other relation did Theia have to Hyperion?",
    "answer": "Sister"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Golden Age author, considered to be the most endearingly affable of all Roman authors, is believed to have complained about a dish with too much garlic to his patron, Maecenas?",
    "answer": "Horace"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work of Horace begins by calling a painter who joined a human head to a horse's neck crazy?",
    "answer": "Ars Poetica / Epistula ad Pisones"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What does Horace call Lucilius?",
    "answer": "His lantern / Light / Lucerna"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Whose political machinations led to the death of her grandson Elagabalus at the hands of the Praetorian guards in 222 AD?",
    "answer": "Julia Maesa"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Elagabalus was not the only person killed by the Praetorian Guard that day. Name his mother who was also killed.",
    "answer": "Julia Soaemias"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When Elagabalus had come to power he had defeated the usurper Macrinus and his son. What was the name of Macrinus' son?",
    "answer": "Diadumenianus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "You are traveling on a spaceship in the farthest frontiers of space. Your ship gets sucked into a black hole, and you are not teleported forward in time, where the Earth is ruled by primates, but back in time - to the glory days of Rome. How would you say, in Latin, 'Take me to your leader'?",
    "answer": "Duce / Ducite me ad ducem tuum / vestrum (imp. mood necessary)"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now that they've taken you to their leader, Caligula, you sit down with him in the triclinium and discuss his military campaigns. Trying to curry favor with him, you want to compliment his victories. How would you say, in Latin, 'These armies, which are the best of all, are invincible.'",
    "answer": "Hi exercitus, qui optimi omnium sunt, invicti sunt"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "After leaving Caligula's company and journeying through the forum, a disheveled old man with a wild beard comes chasing after you - pursuing you through every street and yelling feverishly 'Cave! Spectavi te cadentem e caelo, simulac magnum sonitum audivi! Imperator vult te interficere, quod cogitat te deum esse!' According to the old man, why does the emperor want to kill you?",
    "answer": "He thinks you are a god"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Before they ever fought against each other, the Romans and Carthaginians had been allies. In what year did Rome and Carthage sign their first treaty?",
    "answer": "509 B.C."
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The friendly relations between Carthage and Rome continued well into the third century B.C. Against what common enemy did Carthage and Rome unite in 280 B.C.?",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus (of Epirus)"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Even after the first Punic war, Rome and Carthage maintained amicable relations. What privilege did Rome grant to Carthage during the Truceless war?",
    "answer": "Rome allowed Carthage to recruit mercenaries from Italy"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "A medication has the abbreviation H.S. on it. According to this abbreviation, when should this medication be taken?",
    "answer": "In the hour of sleep / Bedtime"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When should a medication be taken if it has the abbreviation A.C. written on it?",
    "answer": "Before food"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What does it mean if a medication has T.I.D. written on it?",
    "answer": "It should be taken three times a day"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid and to whom: 'Anna soror, quae me suspensam insomnia terrent! Quis novus hic nostris successit sedibus hospes, quem sese ore ferens, quam forti pectore et armis!'",
    "answer": "Dido to Anna"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid and to whom: 'O luce magis dilecta sorori, solane perpetua maerens carpere iuventa nec dulcis natos Veneris nec praemia noris? Id cinerem aut manis credis curare sepultos?'",
    "answer": "Anna to Dido"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid and to whom: 'Egregiam vero laudem et spolia ampla refertis tuque puerque tuus (magnum et memorabile numen), una dolo diuum si femina uicta duorum est.'",
    "answer": "Juno to Venus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb 'parco', give the third person plural imperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "Parcerent"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Change 'parcerent' to the pluperfect.",
    "answer": "Pepericissent"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Make 'pepercissent' passive.",
    "answer": "Parsi essent"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the preposition 'absque'.",
    "answer": "Sine"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The preposition 'apud' has several meanings. What does it mean in the phrase 'Ego sum apud te hodie.'",
    "answer": "At your house"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When found in works of literary criticism, what does the phrase 'apud Vergilium' mean?",
    "answer": "Within the works of Vergil"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What mythological character taught us to never refuse a wedding invitation?",
    "answer": "Chelone"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Into what was Chelone transformed for ditching a wedding?",
    "answer": "Tortoise / Turtle"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Whose wedding was it?",
    "answer": "Zeus and Hera's"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what modern country were all the following cities located: Memphis, Heliopolis, Nicopolis, and Alexandria?",
    "answer": "Egypt"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what modern country were: Verulamium, Deva, Eburacum, and Aquae Sulis located?",
    "answer": "Britain / United Kingdom / England"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what modern country were: Smyrna, Carrhae, Zela, and Ephesus located?",
    "answer": "Turkey"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who, the son of a man who had fought on the losing side at the Battle of Bedriacum, wrote the 'De Vita Caesarum' in which he covered the lives of 12 Caesars?",
    "answer": "Suetonius"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Give the names of the first and last of the 12 Caesars covered in Suetonius' work.",
    "answer": "Julius Caesar and Domitian"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What other biographical work did Suetonius author, of which the 'De Grammaticis et Rhetoribus' is the only extant section?",
    "answer": "De Viris Illustribus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following does not belong by derivation: courage, court, cordial, record?",
    "answer": "Court"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun do we derive the English 'court'?",
    "answer": "Cortex"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun do we derive the English 'record'?",
    "answer": "Recordare"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun gives us the English word 'cordial'?",
    "answer": "Cor / Cordis"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year was a Roman colony founded on the site of Jerusalem by the emperor Hadrian?",
    "answer": "136 A.D"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During construction of the colony, a Pagan temple was built on the future site of the Church of the Holy Sepulchre. To what goddess was the temple dedicated?",
    "answer": "Venus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was the only ally of Perseus turned to stone during confrontation over Andromeda?",
    "answer": "Aconteus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was turned to stone after mocking the love of a Cypriot youth and showing no emotion at his suicide?",
    "answer": "Anaxerete"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was turned to stone when he proved his untrustworthiness when he told a disguised Hermes about Hermes's theft of Apollo's cattle?",
    "answer": "Battus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Thank you for listening to WROM, the premier station for today's hit music, all in Latin! One classic hit song is 'Non potes accipere quod vis' by the Saxa Volvens. What is this song's name in English?",
    "answer": "You Can't Always Get What You Want"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Many modern songs can actually be traced back to ancient Roman melodies - what would we have called in English the hit Roman song 'dum cithara mea leniter lacrimat'?",
    "answer": "While My Guitar Gently Weeps"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What song, probably by the same band, would the Romans have simply called 'Fiat'?",
    "answer": "Let It Be"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following into English: Ille qui numquam errat numquam quid novum captavit.",
    "answer": "He who never makes a mistake has never tried something new."
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following into Latin: If we had not gone to school, we would not have learned Latin.",
    "answer": "Si non ad scholam venissemus, linguam Latinam non didicissemus."
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What shepherd of Priam exposed the infant Paris?",
    "answer": "Agelaus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What son of Priam by Arisbe predicted that Paris would be the ruin of Troy?",
    "answer": "Aesacus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Into what was Aesacus transformed?",
    "answer": "A diver bird"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus ends with the phrase 'surge, amator, i domum' repeated four times?",
    "answer": "Asinaria"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus did the author call Patruos, meaning Uncle, after the uncle of the central figure, Agorastocles?",
    "answer": "Poenulus"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus, containing three separate scenes, was distinctly valued because it was a social document?",
    "answer": "Stichus"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What future enemy of Rome served as an auxiliary commander for the Romans during the siege of Numantia in 133 B.C.?",
    "answer": "Jugurtha"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Numidia city did Jugurtha hold as his capital?",
    "answer": "Cirta"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "With what two half brothers did Jugurtha initially share power?",
    "answer": "Adherbal and Hiempsal"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs 'miror' and 'minor.'",
    "answer": "'Miror' means 'to wonder or be surprised, amazed' and 'minor' means 'to threaten.'"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs 'neco' and 'necto.'",
    "answer": "'Necro' means 'to kill' and 'necto' means 'to intertwine or weave.'"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between 'praeda' and 'praedo.'",
    "answer": "'Praeda' means 'loot, booty, plunder' and 'praedo' means 'pirate.'"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who speaks the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid: 'Aeole, namque tibi divom pater atque hominum rex et mulcere dedit fluctus et tollere vento, gens inimica mihi Tyrrhenum navigat aequor, Ilium in Italiam portans victosque Penates?'",
    "answer": "Juno"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid: 'Tuus, O regina, quid optes explorare labor; mihi iussa capessere fas est'?",
    "answer": "Aeolus"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who says the following lines in Vergil's Aeneid: 'Tantane vos generis tenuit fiducia vestri? Iam caelum terramque meo sine numine, venti, miscere, et tantas audetis tollere moles? Quos ego...?'",
    "answer": "Neptune / Neptunus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Eheu! You have so much homework to do after you get home from this Certamen Tournament that you are SURE you will be finished with it 'ad Kalendas Graecas.' Idiomatically speaking, when will you finish your homework?",
    "answer": "Never"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English phrase, involving airborne animals, is an equivalent to ad Kalendas Graecas?",
    "answer": "When pigs fly"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Pandora was given a box that she was instructed to never open. What other mythological woman of Bisaltian origins reversed the role when she gifted somebody else with a box that came with an ultimatum?",
    "answer": "Phyllis"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "According to some versions, what brother of Demophon was Phyllis' husband, the recipient of the box?",
    "answer": "Acamas"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "After Acamas married Phyllis, he sailed away, but promised to return. Phyllis gave him the box as he departed, instructing him to only open it if he decided that he wasn't going to come back after all. Well, as mythological men were wont to do, Acamas forgot all about his wife and settled happily on Cyprus. After some time, he opened the box and went insane upon seeing its contents. He tried to escape the horrors, but as he was galloping away on his horse, he met a tragic death. What exactly happened to him?",
    "answer": "He fell on his own sword"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Where were the forces of Lars Porsena defeated in 506 B.C.?",
    "answer": "Aricia"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was the victorious general at this battle?",
    "answer": "Aristodemus of Cumae"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Despite fighting on the behalf of the Latins in the battle of Aricia, to what enemy of Rome did Aristodemus offer refuge?",
    "answer": "Tarquinius Superbus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Thank you for listening to WROM, the premier station for today's hit music, all in Latin! What song might the Romans have called 'Finis Gloriae'?",
    "answer": "Edge of Glory"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin, 'I'm on the edge with you.'",
    "answer": "In fine sum tecum"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Lady Gaga song might the Romans have called 'Nata sicut'?",
    "answer": "Born This Way"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In Catullus' 13th poem, he says that a friend of his can have a scrumptious dinner at his place, provided that the friend brings along lots of good food, pretty girls, wine, jokes, and entertainment. To which unfortunate 'friend' does Catullus propose this 'bring your own bottle' policy?",
    "answer": "Fabullus"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Catullus kindly reminds Fabullus to bring his wallet, because Catullus' own is supposedly filled with what?",
    "answer": "Cobwebs"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The one thing Catullus does offer Fabullus is perfume. The scent of this perfume supposedly smells so good that it will make Fabullus wish he was nothing but a what?",
    "answer": "Nose"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What Tegean king bought Arsinoe as a slave and succeeded Echemus on the throne?",
    "answer": "Agapenor"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Agapenor was a suitor of which famous mythological woman?",
    "answer": "Helen"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What city did he found on the island of Cyprus?",
    "answer": "Paphos"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Latin historian participated with Ammianus Marcellinus in Julian's expedition of 363 A.D. against the Persians?",
    "answer": "Eutropius"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which of his works was a compendium of Roman history in 10 books?",
    "answer": "Breviarium Ab Urbe Condita"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At the behest of which emperor, who wanted 'sparknotes' for the long Roman histories, did Eutropius write the Breviarium Ab Urbe Condita?",
    "answer": "Valens"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the Latin verb 'suesco', give the first person plural perfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "Sueverimus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Keeping everything else the same, change this form to the imperfect.",
    "answer": "Sueceremus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Keeping everything else the same, change 'suesceremus' to the pluperfect.",
    "answer": "Suevissemus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What Greek god traveled to a foreign land where, if the writings of Philostratus and Pseudo-Hyginus are to be believed, he would have encountered the Asian deity Durga? He was accompanied, as usual, by his frenzied Bacchants as he attempted to explore India and subject its people to his worship.",
    "answer": "Dionysus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What elderly advisor of Dionysus also was part of his entourage?",
    "answer": "Silenus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who were Dionysus's caretakers on Mt. Nysa? Today, there is a racing horse with the same name.",
    "answer": "The Nysaean Nymphs"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman commander was sent to put down the revolt of the Macedonian pretender Andriscus in 148 B.C.?",
    "answer": "Q. Caecilius Metellus"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "By what other name was Andriscus known?",
    "answer": "Pseudo-Philip(us)"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the third Macedonian War, the Romans had divided Perseus' Macedonian kingdom into four federal republics. What earlier Illyrian had seen his kingdom suffer a similar fate after being defeated by the Romans in 168 B.C?",
    "answer": "Gentius"
},

{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Bob has 3 apples, and Jane has 6 apples. Jane says, 'Dabo patri omnia mala mea.' Bob, upset that Jane will upstage him yet again, replies, 'Oh yeah? Well, dabo patri omnia mala mea et tua!' Are there any grammatical errors in Bob's Latin?",
    "answer": "No"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Jane, always ready to show off her own Latin knowledge, says 'Ha-ha! Sum melior te non solum numerante malis sed etiam dicente linguam Latinam.' What grammatical error in Latin, if any, has Jane made now?",
    "answer": "She uses the abl. pl. of 'malum' instead of the acc. pl."
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Their father, hearing the argument, comes outside and shouts 'Do you kids ever get along?' If Bob translates this phrase into Latin in his head, he comes up with 'Cooperatis, liberi, umquam?' What grammatical error in Latin, if any, has Bob made?",
    "answer": "He forgot to add the enclitic 'ne' to the verb 'cooperatis'"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which book of the Eclogues, known as the Messianic Eclogue was later interpreted by Christian critics as a reference to Christ?",
    "answer": "The Fourth Book"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Other critics believe that Vergil is actually referring to the child of which famous political couple?",
    "answer": "Marc Antony and Octavia"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Yet another group of literary critics believe that Vergil is alluding to the child of his early patron. Who was this patron?",
    "answer": "Asinius Pollio"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What ruler of the Iceni named the Emperor coheir to the kingdom, along with his two daughters, around the year 60 A.D.?",
    "answer": "Prasutagus"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was Prasutagus' more famous wife who led a revolt against the Romans after they disregarded his will?",
    "answer": "Boudica"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What god, often depicted as a serpent or dragon, was an opponent of Zeus in the Titanomachy?",
    "answer": "Typhon"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Where did Typhon hide after his defeat by Zeus?",
    "answer": "Mount Etna"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What monstrous offspring did Typhon father with Echidna?",
    "answer": "Cerberus"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman emperor used the Christians as a scapegoat for the Great Fire of Rome in 64 AD?",
    "answer": "Nero (Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus)"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman emperor began the first empire-wide, organized prosecution of ordinary Christians?",
    "answer": "Gaius Messius Quintus Decius (Augustus)"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman emperor removed the Altar of Victory from the curia in Rome and renounced the title Pontifex Maximus?",
    "answer": "Flavius Gratianus Augustus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What god was cared for by the tribe of the Sintians after falling for nine days from Olympus all the way to Lemnos?",
    "answer": "Hephaestus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Hephaestus then proceeded to bind Hera with fetters to a golden throne to humiliate her in retribution for her unsavory behavior towards him. Who convinced Hephaestus to free her?",
    "answer": "Dionysus"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "On another occasion, Hephaestus caught his wife Aphrodite and her lover Ares in an invisible net as they slept together. In this scenario, who convinced Hephaestus to let the shamed pair go?",
    "answer": "Poseidon"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What member of the imperial courts of Trajan and Hadrian developed the per species technique, which remained the chief form of biography until the 18th century?",
    "answer": "Gaius Suetonius Tranquillus"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What outstanding right did Trajan grant to Suetonius for supervising public libraries, normally reserved for citizens raising three or more children?",
    "answer": "Ius Trium Liberorum"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Praetorian Prefect under Hadrian and patron of Suetonius did he dedicate his De Vita Caesarum to in 121 AD?",
    "answer": "Septicius Clarus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a deponent verb, translate the following English sentence into Latin: Camilla used a sword to kill the enemy.",
    "answer": "Camilla gladio usa est ut hostem necaret."
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Change that Latin sentence to the present subjunctive tense.",
    "answer": "Camilla gladio utitur ut hostem necat."
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Change that Latin sentence to the future perfect tense.",
    "answer": "Does not exist"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Odysseus originally went to the court of Tyndareus in Sparta in order to court his infamous daughter Helen, but instead fell in love with whom, the daughter of Icarius?",
    "answer": "Penelope"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What did Icarius do after Penelope left him decisively for Odysseus, veiling her face in order to show her loyalty to her new husband?",
    "answer": "He erected a statue of modesty."
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What was the name of Icarius' other daughter?",
    "answer": "Iphthime"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive the English word lagoon?",
    "answer": "Lacus - lake or basin or pit"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive the English word sue?",
    "answer": "Sequor - follow or accompany or aim at"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive the English word impudence?",
    "answer": "Pudet - it shames"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king of Pergamum left his entire kingdom to Rome in 133 BC?",
    "answer": "Attalus III"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king of Nicomedia left his entire kingdom to Rome in 74 BC?",
    "answer": "Nicomedes IV"
},
{
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king of Egypt left the kingdom of Cyrenaica to Rome in 96 BC?",
    "answer": "Ptolemy Apion"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Complete the following quotation from the sixth satire of Juvenal: 'Sed quis custodiet _____.'",
    "answer": "Ipsos custodes"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Complete the following quotation from Book III of Horace's Odes: 'Exegi monumentum _____.'",
    "answer": "Aere perennius"
},
{
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Complete the following quotation from Book I of Cicero's De Officiis: 'Non nobis solum _____.'",
    "answer": "Nati sumus"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is found in the sentence: 'Divitiā gaudemus'?",
    "answer": "Cause"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is found in the phrase 'mirabile visu'?",
    "answer": "Specification"
},
{
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is found in the sentence: 'Sulpicia sapientiā praecedit'?",
    "answer": "Specification"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "What city was the capital of the Amazonian empire?",
    "answer": "Themiscyra"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Who was the taskmaster of Bellerophon, who sent him on various missions with the hopes that he would fail?",
    "answer": "Iobates"
},
{
    "category": "Mythology",
    "question": "Name one war-like tribe, which Bellerophon was sent to conquer.",
    "answer": "The Amazons or the Solymi"
}


]
